# NATHAN P. PETERSEN

Madison, WI · (217) 649-4461 · nathan.petersen@wisc.edu

nathanpetersen.com github.com/npetersen2

# **SUMMARY**

Nathan is a 3<sup>rd</sup> year PhD student in Electrical Engineering. His research area is electric drives and control algorithms for bearingless motors. He has a technically diverse skillset developed via experiences in industry, academia, and personal projects. Nathan is personable, a natural leader, and a team player who helps projects succeed.

### **EDUCATION**

UNIVERSITY OF WISCONSIN - MADISON

**B.S. – Computer Science with Distinction**, GPA: 3.720 / 4.0

May 2019

M.S. – Electrical and Computer Engineering, GPA: 3.900 / 4.0

December 2021

Project: Open-Source Hardware and Software for Advanced Motor Drives

Ph.D. – Electrical and Computer Engineering

expected May 2024

Topic: Sensorless Control of Bearingless Motors

Advisor: Prof. Eric Severson

### RESEARCH EXPERIENCE

Research Assistant: Department of Electrical and Computer Engineering, UW-Madison

Jan. 2020 - Present

- Member of WEMPEC: Wisconsin Electric Machines and Power Electronics Consortium
- Embedded system design (PCBs, FPGA, DSP) of platform for controlling advanced electric motors
  - o Lead developer of open-source hardware and firmware: docs.amdc.dev
  - Used by over ten other graduate students in lab for hardware research experiments
- Control methods for bearingless motors: both continuous and discrete-time control theory, field-oriented current regulation, motion control for rotation and levitation, observer-based estimation of system state, self-sensing position and speed estimation for both rotor angle and displacement
- Control simulation and verification via MATLAB/Simulink: model-in-loop (MIL), custom C code software-in-loop (SIL), auto-generate embedded C code and integration into custom control board
- Collaboration with other grad students to develop common lab infrastructure and experiment procedures
- Mentor to several younger students (both MS and undergraduate) on independent study projects
  - o Developed project goals and timeline, regular meetings, hands-on help

# **JOBS & INTERNSHIPS**

Motor Control Engineer: BETA TECHNOLOGIES, Burlington, VT

June 2019 – Dec. 2019

- Ground-up design of hardware and real-time software for inverter on electric airplane propulsion unit
- Implemented sensor-based and self-sensing field-oriented current regulation on PM motor
- Direct hands-on development from initial concept to full 100+ kW dyno testing

Firmware Engineer Intern: SILICON LABS, Austin, TX

Summer 2017, Summer 2018

- Optimized memory usage of embedded digital radio product with pool-based block allocation
- Design of circuit board for customer to interface host system with embedded devices over SPI
- Created system tracing framework for monitoring real-time task scheduling and system utilization

Web Developer: UW-MADISON COMPUTER SYS. LAB (CSL), Madison, WI

March 2016 - Sept. 2018

Worked with other students and full-time staff to create modern web apps for internal and external use

**Software Development Intern:** INTEL CORPORATION, Champaign, IL

Summer 2013, Summer 2014

• Testing of mobile performance tool, developed Android app to visualize metrics & Qt GUI for Pintool

### **TECHNICAL SKILLS & ABILITES**

**Programming Languages:** C, C++, Verilog / SystemVerilog, MATLAB/Simulink, Python, Tcl, Julia, R, Java, HTML, CSS, JavaScript, PHP, SQL, LaTeX

Operating Systems / RTOS: Windows, Linux, ThreadX, FreeRTOS, bare-metal

CAD / EDA / FEA: Altium Designer, Autodesk Eagle, ModelSim, Xilinx Vivado, Solidworks, FEMM, LTspice

Lab Equipment: oscilloscope, logic analyzer, multimeter, power analyzer, function generator, soldering

Embedded Communication Protocols: UART, SPI, I2C, CAN, USB, Ethernet

Embedded Hardware Platforms: Xilinx Zynq-7000 (FPGA + DSP), STM32, EFM32, Arduino

### **PUBLICATIONS**

- N. Petersen, A. Khamitov, T. Slininger and E. L. Severson, "Machine Design and Precision Current Regulation for the Parallel DPNV Bearingless Motor Winding," *IEEE Transactions on Industry Applications*, 2021.
- 2. **N. Petersen**, T. Slininger, and E. L. Severson, "State Estimation and Run-Out Reduction for Magnetically Levitated Motor Systems," 2021 IEEE Energy Conversion Congress and Exposition (ECCE), 2021.

#### AWARDS

# Wisconsin Distinguished Graduate Fellowship

January 2020

- Direct support of graduate studies provided by the UW-Madison Graduate School
- Awarded to about 10% of graduate students at UW-Madison each year

# **Grainger Power Engineering Undergraduate Award**

April 2019

- Recognition of scholarly achievements in the field of power engineering
- 1 of 5 undergraduate awardees at UW-Madison

### **Big Ten Conference Distinguished Scholar Award**

2017-18 Season, 2018-19 Season

- Recognition of student-athletes who have a GPA of 3.7 or higher for the previous academic year
- 1 of 5 awardees from Wisconsin Men's Rowing

# Intercollegiate Rowing Association (IRA) All-Academic Team

2017-18 Season, 2018-19 Season

- Recognition of student-athletes with top academic standing as well as high athletic performance
- 1 of 3 awardees from Wisconsin

### SOCIETIES, ACTIVITIES & SERVICE

- Student member of IEEE Industry Applications Society (IAS)
- Student member of IEEE Power Electronics Society (PELS)
- Technical peer reviewer of publications in IEEE IAS
- STEM outreach to middle school youth across Wisconsin
  - Developed electromagnetic science experiment kits
  - o Kit contains hardware components and custom lab manual describing three experiments
  - o Multiple outreach events during COVID-19 pandemic using online Zoom meeting format